<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Short questions and answers, plainely opening and explaining both the nature and also the vse of the sacraments of baptisme and the Lords Supper Very profitable for all those who desire to know the nature and vse of the said sacraments. By Richard Preston, preacher of the Word of God at Rushden in Northhampton shiere.</title>
            <author>Preston, Richard, d. ca. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10040</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115178</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850397</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850397</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15596</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10040)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15596)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1183:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Short questions and answers, plainely opening and explaining both the nature and also the vse of the sacraments of baptisme and the Lords Supper Very profitable for all those who desire to know the nature and vse of the said sacraments. By Richard Preston, preacher of the Word of God at Rushden in Northhampton shiere.</title>
                  <author>Preston, Richard, d. ca. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 23, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N[icholas] O[kes] for Iohn Bellamine [i.e. Bellamie], and are to be sold at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange [in the shop of N. Bourne],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC; bookseller's name from STC addendum.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Questions touching the sacraments.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Catechisms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sacraments --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15596:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15596:1"/>
            <p>SHORT QVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIONS AND AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, plainely opening and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining both the nature <hi>and alſo the vſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Baptiſme and the</hi> Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Very profitable for all thoſe <hi>who deſire to know the nature</hi> and vſe of the ſaid Sacraments.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Preſton,</hi> Preacher of the Word of God at
<hi>Ruſhden</hi> in <hi>Northhampton ſhiere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>N. O.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamine,</hi> and are to be ſold at the South en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Royall Exchange. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15596:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15596:2"/>
            <head>To his louing and carefull Mother, M. B.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering with my ſelfe (moſt deare and louing mother) the great care that is committed vnto the Gouernours of Families (namely) not onely to prouide things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the wel-being of the<note n="(a)" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.8.</note> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of their Families, both chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſeruants,<note place="margin">Deut. 11.19.</note> but alſo to teach and inſtruct them in the knowledge of God his will, and the right com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with him, in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular parts of his worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: the performance of which
<pb facs="tcp:15596:3"/>thing maketh the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bee both<note n="(*)" place="margin">Pro. 31.15.30.</note> commended of the people of God, and alſo approoued of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.<note place="margin">Eſter 4.16. Gen. 18.19</note> And alſo conſidering, that in regard of the great imployments of my Father, by which he is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily with-held from a constant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding with his Family: In which reſpect, the greater both care and paines lieth vpon your ſelfe. I haue therefore (as a helpe to you in the weightieſt of thoſe your charges) here ſent vnto you certaine Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Anſwers, opening and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining both the nature and alſo the vſe of both the Sacraments of Chriſt his Inſtitution, entreating you in the abſence of my Father<note n="(*)" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.35.</note> (for in his preſence you remaine as a learner, not an inſtructer) you would make it your practiſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct your Family in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them. I hope I ſhal not need
<pb facs="tcp:15596:3"/>to alleadge
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to the performance of this duty, for that which reſteth as a reaſon in all our actions, taketh place in this alſo (namely) the will of him, whoſe will ought to be a law to vs in all things.<note n="*" place="margin">Deut.
11.19.</note> Secondly, if any ſoule periſh for want of the diſcharge of your duty, God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their blood at your hands.<note n="(*)" place="margin">Ez. 33.8 Gal. 6.10.</note> Thirdly, that generall rule taketh place in this thing: <hi>Doe good to all;</hi> If good, what greater then to helpe them to the knowledge of the meanes of ſaluation? if to all, then eſpecially to thoſe whoſe ſoules in a ſpeciall manner you haue the charge of. For the Author of them, hee is a neighbour Miniſter in your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, in whoſe praiſe I ſpare to ſpeake, his workes ſufficiently te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie of him.</p>
            <p>Thus loath too long to keepe you
<pb facs="tcp:15596:4"/>from the peruſall and practiſe of this enſuing Catechiſme, I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly craue both your bleſſing, and prayers vnto the Lord for me, and the reſt of vs whom the Lord hath made you a meanes of our being: that he alſo would giue vs heere an aſſurance, and hereafter a poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an eternall bliſſefull and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wel-being: vnto whoſe graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous protection I commit you, and in whom I euer reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your dutifull and obedient ſonne during life, <hi>I. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15596:4"/>
            <head>Queſtions very profita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to all them that vvould <hi>know, and learne the nature, and</hi> vſe of the Sacraments.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label> 
               <hi>WHat is a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is a viſible ſigne of an inuiſible grace, or an outward Element appoynted of God to confirme our faith of his promiſes.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Of how many parts doth a Sacrament conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of two parts, that is to ſay, of the Element, and the Word.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15596:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Two: Baptiſme and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Why ſayeſt' thou there be but two Sacraments, when wee haue beene, formerly taught, that there are ſeuen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt in the New Teſtament left no more to bee vſed in his Church: as for Matrimony, Order, Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Pennance, and extreame Vnction; they are no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but the Lords Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for their ſeuerall ends.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is the dipping in, or ſprinckling, or waſhing of an Infant in water.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the outward E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement in Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Water.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What doth water ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15596:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The bloud of Chriſt, and reacheth vs that as water waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away the ſpots, and filthines of the body: So the blood of Chriſt doth purge, and cleanſe our ſoules from all filthy, and deadly ſinnes. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 107.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>To whom doth Baptiſme appertaine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To the Sonnes of the Couenant, and to all beleeuers. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.36.37. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Why ſhould Infants bee baptized, who by reaſon of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of their age cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though Infants haue no power to beleeue, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their beleefe, yet they haue faith imputed vnto them for the promiſe ſake, becauſe they bee the ſeede of the faithfull.
<hi>Gen.</hi> 17.6.7.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15596:6"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What if Infants die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Gods promiſe is not in vaine vnto them for default of the Sacrament; for the Spirit of God is not ſo bound to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that it cannot worke where the water wanteth, or that it muſt bee alwayes there where the water is ſprinkled: True be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, old or young, are not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe they are outwardly waſhed with water, but becauſe they be Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through grace: <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.5.8.
<hi>Ro.</hi> 11.5.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not Baptiſme be neglected?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, but with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence it ought to be embraced: he that neglecteth it, neglecteth the Author of it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the vſe of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, it is an euident teſtimony that God the Father
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15596:6"/>in his Sonne Chriſt hath freely for giuen vs all our ſinnes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it putteth vs in minde, that foraſmuch as wee are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Souldiers of Chriſt, we ought, 1. To fight againſt all the enemies of ſaluation. 2. To mortifie all vncleane luſts. 3. To die vnto ſinne: and 4. To a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe new men, bearing the image of Chriſt, and faſhioning our ſelues after his example. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.4.5.
<hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.1.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How is the other Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Why is it called a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe it was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and eaten at night.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Hath it no other name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, it is called the Lords Table, a Communion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15596:7"/>the Euchariſt, or thankſgiuing, &amp;c. 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16.21.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Is it not called the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Altar?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, I finde no ſuch name giuen to it in the whole booke of God: The Papiſts vſe that name, that their daily ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe might find credit.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But tell me, what is the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is an heauenly ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, wherein all the faithfull do ſpiritually through faith, both eate the body of Chriſt, and drinke his blood, vnto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of their faith, the comfort of their conſcience, and the ſaluation of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Who is the Author of this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26.27.28.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15596:7"/>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23.24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>When did hee inſtitute this Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Preſently after the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Paſſeouer, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before his death.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What are the outward elements in this Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Bread, and wine.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How do they differ from ordinary bread and wine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They differ not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but in vſe and quality: Common bread, and common wine are appointed of the Lord for the alone nouriſhment of the body: but this holy bread, and wine are appointed to bee ſignes of the body and blood of Chriſt, whereby our ſoules are nouriſhed.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What is the Analogie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſignes, and the things
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15596:8"/>ſignified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It ſtandeth in feeding, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, comforting, refreſhing, in vnion, and communion.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Shew it more plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As the bread and wine do feede, nouriſh, comfort, and refreſh our bodies: So the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and blood of Chriſt (with the merits of his paſſion,) doe ſpiritually feede, nouriſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and refreſh our hungry ſoules. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.32.33.35.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Shew me our vnion with Chriſt in this Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As that which we eate and drinke, is turned to fleſh &amp; blood, and incorporate into vs: So our eating, and drinking this banquet by faith, doeth tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vs (as it were) into Chriſt, and maketh vs fleſh of his fleſh,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15596:8"/>and bone of his bone. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.56.
<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Shew me our Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with our brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> As many cornes, and grapes are vnited into one loafe, and one wine, euen ſo wee as many members, are vnited into one myſticall body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Chriſt is the head.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Tell mee, why are there two Elements in the Lords Supper, and but one in Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is ſet before vs as a lauer, and water is ſufficient to waſh away filthineſſe from our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: But in the Lords Supper he is ſet before vs as heauenly foode: wherein bread without wine is not ſufficient. For as meate alone doth not nouriſh the body, but there is required
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15596:9"/>drinke. So to the nouriſhment of our ſoules it is not enough ſpiritually by faith to eate the bread, but we muſt alſo drinke the wine.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Is wine as neceſſary as bread to this Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, altogether as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; and therefore much do the Papiſts wrong Chriſtians, that with-hold the cup from them.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What be the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall rites?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They bee either ſuch things, as concerne the Miniſter, namely to bleſſe, breake, powre, giue; or the people, as to take, cate, drinke.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What do theſe rites ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They ſignifie ſpirituall things. To bleſſe, ſignifieth the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15596:9"/>duty of the Miniſter, whereby he calleth vpon God by prayer, that theſe outward Elements might be conſecrated, and ſet apart to an holy vſe. The brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the bread, and powring of the wine, ſignifieth the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the body, and the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the blood of Chriſt. The giuing of the ſignes doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the voluntary gift of Chriſt, that he made himſelfe a free-wil Offering to take away the ſins of his people. To take, ſignifieth our apprehenſion of Chriſt by faith: and to cate and drinke, our vnion with him, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with our brethren.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What do you gather from hence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, that wee are moſt vile ſinners,
<hi>Pro.</hi> 20.9. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.10. Secondly, that wee deſerue the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15596:10"/>intollerable torments of hel fire euerlaſtingly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.2.3 Thirdly, the great loue of God in ſending his Sonne to take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him our nature, and to dye for vs, to our redemption. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.10.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the great loue of Chriſt and his humility to humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto the curſed death of the Croſſe, and torments of hell for our ſaluation. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5.6.7.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Hauing gone thus with you, I pray you tell me whether we doe really eate and drinke the body and blood of Chriſt in this Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: for firſt, that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the nature of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it cannot bee both the ſigne, and the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it were to deny the Aſcenſion, and interceſſion of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15596:10"/>Chriſt, and to affirme that the Reſurrection is paſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it were to make the body of Chriſt but a phantaſie, and the forme of a body.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it were to make Chriſts body a monſtrous body, and to be in many places at one time.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, this Sacrament would be a Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, then the damned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates ſhould eate Chriſts fleſh, and be ſaued, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.54.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, it were to deny that Chriſt tooke fleſh of the Virgin, if bread and wine do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his fleſh; or elſe to ſay, he had a mixed body; either of which is blaſphemy, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Rom.</hi>
1.3.</p>
            <p>Eightly, it were to affirme, that Chriſts body is dead, which is

<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15596:11"/>abhominable; and how could it be eaten vnleſſe it be dead? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But Chriſt ſaid, This is my body, therefore the bread is his body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not ſo: Our Sauiour calleth himſelfe a Vine, a Dore, a Rock; hee is alſo compared to a theefe, to a day-ſtarre. Is Chriſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Vine, a Dore, a Rocke, a theefe, and a Day-ſtarre? No, it is an abſurde concluſion. So hee calleth bread his body, not that it is his body, but a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and figure of his body.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How is Chriſt preſent in the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not bodily, but ſpiritually by grace, <hi>Mat.</hi>
18.20. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>To whom muſt this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament be adminiſtred?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To ſuch as can examine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15596:11"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What ſay you of children, fooles, madmen, &amp;c. may not they be admitted to this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In no ſort: Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot examine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Secondly, leſt they heape vpon themſelues, the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord, &amp; be guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What doe you thinke of open ſinners, may they be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of this holy Communion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: not till they haue repented of their ſinnes, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured earneſtly to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto God &amp; their brethren.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>It ſeemes that this holy Supper belongs to none but to the faith full and penitent perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The fruite and benefit of Chriſts Paſſion belongs one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them, but yet many other beſides them partake of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15596:12"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Doe not all that eate the externall ſignes, receiue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fit of Chriſts death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: for firſt, all haue not faith, <hi>Tit.</hi>
1.1.2. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. Secondly, they haue not the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, which things ſhold make them worthy receiuers of the benefits of Chriſts death.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Can the wicked get any harme by eating the Sacramentall ſignes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes verily: For firſt, they eate and drinke their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Secondly, they are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the body and blood of Chriſt. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.27.29.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>When is this Supper to be receiued?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Then, when occaſion therof is offered; and neceſſary it is, that it ſhould be eaten often, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15596:12"/>11.26.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Where ſhould it bee ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the publicke congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation: where many are met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for that end, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What ſay you to them that are lame and ſicke, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come to the houſe of God; ought they to receiue this ſupper in their priuate families?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I doe not deny but that they may, ſo bee it there be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gathered to them to make vp a congregation, who may partake with them.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>To whom doth the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of this Supper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To them who are fit Miniſters of the Word.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>What ſay you then to a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15596:13"/>dumbe dogge? Hee is no fit Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and therefore his ſacrament is no ſacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not ſo: For firſt, though he be no fit Miniſter of God, yet becauſe he is come in the roome of a Miniſter, by the election of the Church, we muſt not refuſe him, nor his Sacrament. 2. Beeing enabled by the Church to giue what he can, though hee come neuer ſo inordinately to adminiſter this Sacrament, yet he muſt not be reiected, but wee muſt receiue what hee can giue. Thirdly, we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betweene a calling, and the execution of it; for it proues not, he hath no calling, becauſe he executeth it not: as a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ceaſeth not to be a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or to want office, becauſe he doth not duely execute it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15596:13"/>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How may I communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with a wicked Minister?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The wickedneſſe of a Miniſter doth not pollute the Sacrament to a worthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Why?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, a good Miniſter doth not make it the better to a bad man, therefore not a bad Miniſter the worſe to a good man. Secondly, the efficacy of the Sacrament depends onely vpon Gods promiſe, and the faith of the beleeuer, not on mans goodneſſe or badneſſe. A meſſage may bee as truely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by a bad man as a good, and good waxe will receiue an impreſſion as well by a brazen ſeale, as a golden one.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But hee is a graceleſſe man, and how can hee then bee a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15596:14"/>meanes of conueying grace to mee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Grace is compared to water; now may not water that paſſeth through a ſtony chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, which it ſelfe is ſo vndiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that it cannot haue any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of it, make a whole gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruitfull? Thus ſtands the caſe with a graceleſſe Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But by communicating with him, ſhall I not communicate in his ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, if you made him not miniſter, nor allow of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency, but communicate onely in the Lords ordinance ſo farre as he is able to adminiſter it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>With whom may I right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communicate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> With ſuch as are of a godly life and conuerſation. Firſt, becauſe we profeſſe our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15596:14"/>ſelues members, and fellow Chriſtians with them. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe we deſire to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in that Communion. Thirdly, becauſe our loue and zeale may bee better ſtirred vp by the prayers, and examples of ſuch.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How may I partake where open ſinners are tollerated to receiue the Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No mans ſinne can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file another, or make Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or the ſeale of it, in vaine to him, that is no way acceſſary to it; neither hath it power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from the Sacrament. <hi>Ezek.</hi>
18.20, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5. Secondly, Chriſt entred into the ſame Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with wicked perſons, and eat the ſame Paſſeouer with <hi>Iudas,</hi> and was vndefiled. <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.22.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we are not ſo bound
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15596:15"/>to examine the vnworthines of others, as of our ſelues: which maketh the Apoſtle ſay, Let a man examine himſelfe, and not another man, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 28. By theſe reaſons wee ſee that the wickedneſſe of another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant, doth not preiudice him that is rightly prepared.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>To conlude, ſeeing that I haue learned of you the nature of this Sacrament, and where, when, of whom, and with whom to receiue the ſame; now I would gladly know of you, to what end &amp; vſe the Lord Ieſus inſtituted this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Firſt, to put vs in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that loue, and fellowſhip which ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, being all members of one myſticall body. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4.5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17.12.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſtirre vs vp vnto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15596:15"/>continuall thankfulneſſe vnto God the Father, for the great benefits wee haue receiued of him by the death of his Sonne. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.46.47.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, to put vs in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that his body was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and his bloud ſhed for our redemption. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Mat.</hi>
26.28. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19.</p>
            <trailer>FINI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
